in ballet they say the first few moves
determine the
whole practice like if the first few
moves
are are well done then the rest goes
well and if the first few moves are
lazily done then the rest is poorly done
so go right to your breath very strong
single
pointed focused on your
breath
e e
and go to the golden
one
e e
and come to the Bliss cut and I feel a
good everyone's feeling that feeling of
contentment or satisfaction
or Surrender to
the to where you are and be happy
contented stay in the sky no need to go
anywhere else this is the best thing you
can do to help all the people around you
just stay in the sky right now stay here
where you are now and that's the best
service you can do for
others
e
e e
then come to the mountains look at the
mountains across the
valley and sunlight on the
valy
e e
come back to the Golden
Moon ask your teacher to come
you can place your head on their
chest like a
baby just feel the
comfort of having your head on their
chest
they there're like embrace it holding it
like a baby
let that be your single
Focus like a child sleeping at her
mother's
breath feel
Comfort protection
and stay there in that feeling don't
feel any need to come back here or any
other place stay there in that feeling
of safety and care of your
teacher
e
e e
and slowly come back to this
room and you can open your eyes for
it for
concentration feels really really good
really really good I think it's the best
group I ever meditated with actually
seriously the previous record holder was
the Willcox 20 years to life
prison they're
good really honestly they're really good
they don't have anywhere else to
go uh sorry not Willcox
Douglas but uh that's like this one of
the sweetest meditations I thought
you're doing really
well
okay we we got up to
uh we got up to things being uh a
product of
names right names meaning in this
philosophy names meaning the images
produced in your mind by the seeds of
how you've treated others in the
past which means that things are not as
he says Su Tupa okay Su Tupa is a very
unusual word and it means
uh independent or
self-standing
so so Nick for example is not as
concrete as we thought he was he's more
fluid okay or whoever you are UT whoever
you are it doesn't matter you're not as
fixed as you thought you were you are as
fluid as the
seeds firing in your mind at any given
moment right and and then they will
determine who you are and what you are
even what life form you are
okay so we're not as fixed
or it's not that you die as a human and
then get born as a dog right it's that
you're the
same difference in the firing of the
seeds that caused your your last bite of
dinner to go
down could also turn you into a
dog it's that scary okay that the seeds
that went off to see you
swallow are are not much different than
the seeds that would go off to see you
as a dog for the next 15 years you see
it's the same process the same thing
it's just seed firing you see and we
have plenty of seed to be a dog okay all
right we're just lucky they haven't gone
off yet
uh
uh we are not so fixed or concrete
sou due to
the what do you call due to the
Confluence of many different factors and
causes for example
he says seed water fertilizer heat and
moisture
right I sort of object to that kind of
language cuz he didn't
put he didn't put
projection that seed he's talking about
is like a corn seed or something so I I
think it's sort of
dangerous to present dependent
origination as just seeds and factors
you see you got got to throw in at least
one kic ripening cuz otherwise it's just
conventional things it's not going to
change how you lead your
life so depend origination means that
things
are those of you know about but want to
learn to
button means occurs in
Reliance means happens Independence you
see there are
synonyms and tun are are synonyms
sometimes T is given as a sort of a
definition of Dum so what they translate
as dependent
origination can be described as
happening in
Reliance
okay uh to
you can see this going on all around you
that things depend on their
causes but just to pause here we
uh we misidentify the connection between
the result and the cause for example
with the aspirin you see we we
draw uh an artificial link between uh
the headache going away and the presence
of sumptin in the pill you see I mean we
we draw a false link of causation we
believe that the headache goes away
because of some chemical in the pill you
see and they're not
relating okay the headache hasn't gone
away because of the presence of some
chemical in the pill because if that
were the case then every time you took
that pill your headache would go away so
it's not that
uh we constantly draw false connections
between what's happening to us or why a
car goes you you draw you draw a
connection between the presence of
gasoline and the car running and there's
no such connection okay so we are
constantly misunder understanding
dependent
origination we we constantly drawing
false lengths
just you know as a little hint from
Planet B to Planet
a uh if the same causes are
present and the same effect doesn't
happen then that ain't the
cause got it
okay you you keep taking an aspirin and
your headache doesn't go out
in
okay it's kind funny
okay okay now we get into the two Tas
okay t means
uh my my uh tiet Lama's name was
andin his name means gone to the Limit
okay so the the edge of the of this
platform is called T So t means an edge
it can also mean a
cliff okay and then Tarin his name was
gone to the Limit gone gone to the end
of Enlightenment right T
so now we're going to start talking
about uh T in the sense of an extreme
okay that you could fall into and again
a good example would be when we got
here uh we didn't
drive we we we followed Google what do
you call it the what do you call it GPS
thing GPS thing you know said take four
turns off of the last rer which were all
icebound and and uh we got through two
of them uh then we got into this weird
thing where we couldn't go forward
without sliding off the road and we
couldn't get up back either so we just
had to stop and then cars started to
pile up in front of us and behind us and
they were quite irritated and you know
anyway and then that guy came out and
said I'll drive your car down for you
and I'm like he says don't worry there's
there's a ditch on either side and
they're big
but you can't see him because of the
snow and I'm like this is supposed to
comfort me you know you know and I could
just see him like going off the road and
amputating his leg and I'm paying
Insurance the rest of my life I'm like
let's just stay here until the to try
comes you know
uh so that's it t the two ditches are T
to
means you don't want to slide off into
either clear
okay you don't want to fall off either
Cliff what are the two
Cliffs and this gets into one of the
most beautiful statements in all of
Buddhist scripture okay and it's it's
Jets Kapa who did it but there's a few
uh opening acts
okay we are seeking to deny the extreme
that something could be exist existing
in a independent or natural way
okay which would which which would imply
that it existed without ex without
depending on any other thing when now
you know when I say that meaning it
existed without depending on your seeds
firing some seeds going on okay uh
that's that's what it means to use
dependent origination as a
reason or a
justification that things
are empty okay that they are coming from
your
seeds
now and that's why in scripture we see
those famous
lines say say in your head
n that's a big
[Laughter]
head okay y means the extreme of
thinking things exist okay the extreme
of thinking things exist
uh and it's one of the two ditches in
life okay that you don't want to slide
into that you don't want to think things
exist Does that mean Nick doesn't exist
no what would it be to fall into the
extreme of thinking that Nick exists it
would be to think that Nick was out
there and that the way I see him is not
coming from my own seats okay a Nick who
existed without coming from my own Seas
is is the extreme of a Nick who exists
okay so you have to add the extra words
the extreme of Nick
existing independent of the seeds in my
own mind okay that's that's called the
extreme of thinking that things exist
does Nick exist yes can Nick shave
we're not
sure we don't have any evidence either
way
uh yeah I mean he can look in the mirror
and he can you know let's say brush his
teeth okay uh he can that's okay there's
a Nick there he is brushing his teeth
okay to think there's a Nick in the
mirror and you're brushing his teeth is
not the extreme of thinking things exist
the ex dream of thinking things exist
would be to look in the mirror and say
what you see is not coming from how you
treat
others okay and the relative
pleasantness of what you see is not
specifically related to the your ability
to hold your
temper okay cuz that's the source of
beauty that's the karmic seed for beauty
is the ability to hold your temper and
not get upset or angry
if you want to make your face age
fast or if conversely you want to save a
lot of money on
makeup uh just be patient with people
don't get angry
easily all
[Music]
right
uh so we can say
that it's very famous language in in The
Emptiness teachings
n the
appearance the appearance of things the
appearance of
things prevents us from falling into the
ditch of saying things exist the
appearance of things prevents us from
falling into the ditch of see saying
things exist so you now know that the
appearance of things must here
mean understanding that what appears
around you is coming from seeds in your
own mind which were planted by how good
you were to others okay and
understanding that what appears around
you is coming from how you treat
others what which in the scripture is
called
appearance
uh prevents you from
believing uh in the nick that was never
there that was the Nick who didn't
deserve to be criticized okay
okay so very famous the appearance of
things understood correctly prevents us
from believing in the nick who was never
there all
right that the extreme of thinking
things exist meaning a Nick who isn't
there okay
sh which is to say he says
if you understand that the fact that
things come from other
things if you understand that things
come from other
things uh then you
sorry can you come to a
realization that understanding that
things come from other things is the
friend of emptiness okay it's the screen
and the projector thing we talked about
yeah they are they
are different sides of the same coin
okay they are different sides of the
same coin you look at the coin from one
side it's the blank screen you look at
the coin from the other side it's the
fact that your seeds are projecting what
everything you see and together they
explain the existence of all things
okay and if you understand
the if you understand the how things are
coming from your seeds Okay you won't
fall into the Trap of thinking that
things exist the way you always thought
they did cars run from
gas work results in
money uh negotiating with your boyfriend
makes him
reasonable uh no they're all the same uh
taking more pills will remove your hen
you know like things like that okay
if something like a sprout coming up out
of the ground right that first little
Sprout of a flower it was really
exciting and in the whole next 8 months
there were wild flowers all over the
front of my house everywhere and they
they went off at different times of the
Season there's still some going off in
the middle of winter uh but you know we
planted them in a be ground and in the
excitement of the first not even open
Leaf just it came up it comes up uh half
half and then it opens like that and it
was about this big uh so
the
uh if that
Sprout
existed in itself right remember in when
you get tired of MAA language just say
in okay I think it's very powerful it's
extremely normally the shoulder is more
powerful right Miles Davis
said you
say more less is more M Davis said less
is more uh so it's that way with majima
also
so if the Sprout were in the Sprout or
if the Sprout were coming from the
Sprout then nothing could change the
Sprout okay because nothing would
be acting on the Sprout the Sprout would
be acting on itself you see
if if a sprout were in the Sprout it
would be independent of all other
conditions affecting it okay if the
Sprout is coming from seeds in your
mind you
know if the Sprout is coming from how
you treat other people then then you can
change the Sprout and then a sprout can
change because it's it's depending on
other factors if it were self-contained
it would always be the
same okay if it were self-contained it
would never change it would never open
the the two little leaves would never
split and then you'd never have a flower
6 months later it's just not possible if
it were self-contained if it were
relying on something outside of it
meaning your seeds in your mind then
then all things are possible then a seed
can grow then a sprout can grow then you
can have flowers in 6 months cuz they
are not coming from the
Sprout they are coming from shifts in
the season your mind what caused the
wild flowers to flower in my garden
throughout the summer and fall and a few
are still going off okay is nothing to
do with the seeds or the Sprout under
the ground these
are moment to moment ripening of seeds
in my own mind and that's the only way
it could be if it existed in the Sprout
if the Sprout were in the Sprout it
would always be a sprout it would never
change to a flower okay could it it
would always be a sprout it would be
stuck being a sprout if it existed the
way you always felt it did all right
here we go
so if the
Sprout
uh
were
itself and only itself it if it were
self-contained then it couldn't
change but because it doesn't have its
own nature okay that's a difficult
expression okay get used to
means
right uh does it exist through some
nature of its
own or does it have a nature of its own
so what do you mean when you say that g
what do you mean when it's when you say
something has a nature of its own well
pick something that you can quickly
identify its nature what's the nature of
a fire it's hot okay the nature of fire
basic nature of fire is that it's hot
in Buddhism it's called
sash definition of fire is that which is
hot and burning so let's stick to Heart
okay the hotness of Fire doesn't come
from the fire okay the hotness of Fire
doesn't come from the
fire how
hot fire feels to you
is coming from you okay how hot even so
basic a thing as the very characteristic
which defines a fire is not natural to
the
fire it's coming from you which it means
that someone could touch fire or put
their hand in
fire if they had special seeds and it
and it wouldn't feel hot to them so you
know these pis in India
there they just pick
up Cs and and you're like
you know and they they do all they pick
up all the fire it's considered a
important uh skill for proar I don't
know what they do with all the kids who
can't pick up fire they they probably
get fired or something
um but uh really every every good parari
like in Kashi in vasi they can they just
pick up the coals and they then they
blow on them and then they put them back
and and you're like you can't even bear
watch him do it you know but it means
that they're not feeling the fire in the
same way I would for whatever reason
maybe they got calluses I don't know but
uh but that means the fire is not as hot
to
them okay
uh so even the characteristic which
defines that object is not inherent to
it
okay fire is not heat is not in fire I
like that in we got to go for that okay
okay heat is not in the
fire the capacity to take away your
headache is not in the aspirin there's
nothing inherent in
anything
uh where is
[Music]
that therefore because the Sprout
doesn't have a quality of being a sprout
in
it uh it can change its
makeup means uh here it
means its circumstances the
circumstances of the Sprout can change
uh how it can slowly evolve into in
eventually into hay or straw so they're
just giving an
extreme you start with a sprout it
becomes grass it gets becomes older
grass it becomes grass which has dyed
and then that grass is sied and brought
into the to the barn and dried and
becomes straw okay so all the way from
seed to
straw all each change that it can go
through must be coming from your mind
because if it were a sprout in a sprout
it would never stop being a sprout okay
it couldn't change cuz it's a spra and
it's not
straw okay that came
later so it must be coming from your
mind all the way up to into bed barley
was important okay so they say also
barley the two most important things you
know hay to feed your yak and barley to
eat
yourself things evolve things
change and then even up to the fact that
animals or humans can eat
them all
those phases or seasons of
objects especially uh crops for example
uh they're all teaa
means it's cool it works it happens you
know it operates
there if if the Sprout were were the way
if it existed the way you always thought
it did then uh it would always be a
sprout if it was coming from itself it
would always be itself and then it would
be a sprout forever see if it's coming
from you and from seeds firing in your
mind and if the seeds fire in a
different order or one seed fires and
then wears out and then another seed
replaces it and fires then you can
perceive the Sprout uh growing into a
stock and then giving leaves and then
giving flowers and then drying out and
then people what do you call it
winnowing that stuff and then people
eating it
okay
so so now we have the other half of the
equation before we had
now we
have very
famous again means the extreme of
thinking that things existed the way you
thought they did you know you thought a
sproud had some kind of magical power in
it which allowed it to transform into a
stem which allowed it to transform into
a leaf and which allowed it to transform
into a
fruit but some Sprouts die
and they never
become fruit or
grain okay
why and then a scientist wants to say it
didn't have the right heat or there
wasn't enough rain or you know it didn't
have the right DNA or anything like that
but that also is coming from
you okay in the end you have to
explore why did this crop fail from from
lack of rain
and the other crop didn't fail from lack
of
rain even if you say it was the rain
well who caused the rain why did rain
fall there and not there oh there was a
wind or there was you know and then
scientists are just chasing their tails
you know oh there was a
wind
duh you know why did the wind come up oh
the sun Shone on that part of the ocean
it didn't shine on the on the land
why because Light Came From the Sun and
didn't hit the water and hit the
land
why how does light come from the sun we
talked about it in yoga class the other
day you know there there's no uh quantum
physics has proven that it's impossible
it's not possible for light to be coming
from the
sun light behaves in two contradictory
ways according to where the Observer is
positioned
could be either particles moving in a
straight line or ripples moving out like
that and canceling each other in a in a
distinctive pattern that's only possible
for
ripples so at the same time it's
Rippling at the same time it's shooting
in a straight line is not possible okay
depending on where the Observer is
located okay so don't tell me with this
sun the light from the sun hit the ocean
which caused the wind which caused the
cloud which caused the rain which caused
your C to
fail you're just you're just giving me
an endless chain of things
that that don't explain the thing before
it okay all right uh okay and then when
you get down to the the primary cause of
how matter itself moves you can't
explain it and then you tell me it it
can't be what it is you know you you
chase Your Tail Back to the point where
you can't explain
anymore you
know
okay
uh okay
so okay very famous if one extreme is to
think that Nick existed the way we
thought he
did which was if Nick seems irritable it
has nothing to do with
me right if Nick seems irritable it has
nothing to do with me that's how you
used to think he existed okay to believe
he could be irritable and it has nothing
to do with you is the extreme of
thinking he exists okay that's what it
means to say the extreme of thinking he
exists a Nick who could be
irritable without my having been
irritable in the past is a non
possibility there's no such thing that's
the extreme of thinking Nick exists so
what's the opposite what's meta what's
the extreme of thinking Nick doesn't
exist
okay uh
statistically the people who fall
into Nick exists versus the people who
fall into Nick doesn't exist are about
99,999 over here to one over here okay
why this extreme means you went to a bad
teaching about
emptiness and they said Nick's not what
you thought he was and then you decide
Nick doesn't
exist then if
Nick's if Nick if Nick who's irritable
from his own side can't exist then Nick
can't exist there's no such thing as
Nick everything's an
illusion uh I can cheat him I can lie to
him I can steal from him it doesn't
really matter does it Lama Ora
I think the baby was noisy tonight or
anyway she told me this cute story her
mother was a disciple of one famous
Rabbi I I don't know I don't remember
his name but he was a very charismatic
teacher and she became his disciple and
then you know the
usual jealousy trips were going on
between the leading
disciples and then
uh which which I was very guilty of I I
I had a 20e jealousy trip the only
reason it's not going on now is I'm in a
different state
um but
uh but you know there was uh I forget
what it was oh yeah uh so they were
having a big dinner and all the close
disciples were cooking and then uh her
mother came out I don't know whether a
tray of potatoes in a
glass Tupperware thing and then she
slipped and dropped it you know and then
there was a big crash and the potatoes
went all over the floor and then the the
the other leading disciple who was
jealous of her said ha
Karma you know and then the the guru
came down the stairs and walked over to
that lady and stamped on her foot and
said hahaa karma
[Laughter]
why did I bring that
up yeah oh oh so what it yeah lots of
people fall into this one oh you
know uh
Nick the the you call the Nick as I see
him is the one that's really there okay
and it cannot be coming from my mind cuz
I've never been that
irritable
um you're
right uh the seed is always smaller than
the result okay you can always Comfort
yourself in in in every misery you
encounter and every bad thing that
someone does to you you can always
Comfort yourself
that that whatever you did was less okay
uh that doesn't really help though uh so
if someone says Nick is not the way you
thought Nick is just in your mind right
then the other extreme is to say well
then then it doesn't matter what I do
with I can do anything I want with Nick
cuz he's just a mental
Apparition he's an operation of my mind
I can treat him any way I want it's just
Karma okay that's I think that's why I
brought that up uh it's just Karma it's
just an apparition you see so that would
be the Other Extreme so this extreme is
relatively much less common than the
other one this one is a we call
uh K as opposed to means inborn
mistake yut is mostly an inborn mistake
most people have it when they're born
then MAA is a learned mistake it's it's
a result of bad learning it's a result
it's an acquired t
okay it's an acquired
T So then he says
here right the belief that Nick exists
the way you thought he did is removed by
understanding how he's coming from your
seats the belief that Nick has no
existence at all is removed by the
understanding of
emptiness and that's very subtle and you
got to think about it
okay it would seem
that the belief in emptiness would
thrust you into believing nothing
exists and it would seem that in
understanding of how things are coming
from your seeds would thrust you into a
belief about how things exist but it is
rather the opposite and you have to chew
on that and I'm not going to give it to
you okay you have two on that okay why
would in understanding that things are
coming from seeds remove your belief
that things
exist and why would in understanding
that things are empty remove your belief
that things don't exist because the
opposite would seem the case okay and
you have to chew on that you have to
think about it okay it's very it took me
a long time I remember okay
uh emptiness will Express itself as
projection to a well educated man
[Applause]
okay so there's a Sutra sutras are
usually named after the person who who
brought up a question
okay body
you know means who asked the question
and then they they're named after the
person who asked the question so there's
a Naga King named
madrea uh which
means H it's a reference to the lake
that he lives in and it's never warm m
okay
M uh so anyway this Naga King ask Lord
Buddha a question and then in that Sutra
the following lines come
uh when you're reading a quotation you
know okay just for you Tibetan
freaks then you you give it this little
flourish with the tone of your voice at
the
end and that means a quote is ending
okay or you can say
b
b which means
B
okay so
anyway if you hear a llama being
translated and then they'll say they'll
say something
like and it means he
said it it means you're supposed to
translate the llama said okay so if it
if it irritates you you know where it's
coming from
uh anything that has been born from
causes was never
born it has no nature of being
born what does emptiness mean emptiness
means that the thing came from its
causes that's beautiful see that's the
point he's trying to get us to the point
where you get confused about the two
sides of the coin somebody comes up to
you says what is emptiness you say it's
things are coming from the seeds in your
mind is that true no emptiness is an
absence of something but it means you're
you're so you understand emptiness so
well that when somebody asks you what
emptiness is you go straight to the
pagination what's empty guing Michael
the Pen's coming from
you
okay
uh anyone who grasps emptiness this
deeply
is that now we're going to get on to
another subject okay we're going to get
on to a whole new subject
okay uh we got time for this
yeah
uh but
B is an expression that means to be
careful okay b means to be careful it
deres from an old word pagma bakma means
a newly wedded bride okay pagma means a
newly wedded woman so you know in Tibet
in ancient
times uh there was this whole ritual you
know the you would decide to get married
to a
girl and or the parents would decide and
then you would
uh she would have to move from her
family to her husband's family to their
yurt or to
their I mean that's what it was and then
uh there was this whole procession thing
where the man's brothers would get on
horses and go get the lady and bring her
back
and install her in the house you know
where she became the slave of his mother
Forever Until the mother passed away
from natural hopefully natural
[Music]
C okay so uh that was the system and she
just became the slave of the family she
was lower than everybody and she had to
do everybody's dirty work uh and so and
she wasn't supposed to talk you know
she's just supposed to do what she's
told to do and that and so pagma to be a
newly wedded bride became an the the
word you use to describe someone who
was like I don't know wasn't allowed to
talk or you know or was timid it became
a word for
timid okay and then it became a word for
uh
extremely mindful like never say
anything in front of the
Mother-in-law okay so B later became
came to mean
careful and then later in majima it came
to mean
aware of what's really going on you know
like quietly observant of what's really
going on so bagya came to mean wise you
know like quietly observant of what's
going on on so what the scripture is
saying whoever
understands that emptiness expresses
itself as the seeds in your
mind that person has the capacity to act
properly okay so now bakya has come to
mean they
have they're careful about what they do
they're careful about what they do
get this okay I'll tell you what I'll
tell you the punchline and then we'll go
through the joke
okay
uh if you've gotten a correct teaching
on
emptiness what does your attitude about
collecting Karma
become you know what's how's your belief
in
seeds is
it is it strengthened or is it weakened
I mean the fact of
ESS justifies the theory of se you see
what I mean you a person who really
understands emptiness becomes seed
anal okay no then they're like keeping a
book They say six times forget it I'm
doing 12 times you know okay okay I want
a 12 time book or a 36 time book know
let's get serious here everything's
coming from my se you know everything's
coming from my se you know and then the
the greater your understanding of
emptiness the greater your interest in
ethical living and the greatest the
greater your interest in being kind to
others and taking care of others a how a
person acts from hour to hour is a
direct reflection of how well they
understand emptiness if they are being
unkind to others uh demanding lying
hurting others abrupt with others unkind
undiplomatic anything un anything any
kind
of of negative behavior even the
slightest towards another person that
that person doesn't understand emptiness
or that or they may understand it and
not be aware of it the greater your
understanding of emptiness the Kinder
more graceful more considerate more neat
more everything you become okay and and
they're just a direct correlation you
could you could tell if a a sage
understands emptiness from how they
treat other people if there's any kind
of roughness or impoliteness or any kind
of any kind of misbehavior then then
they don't understand emptiness okay and
and you don't hear that very often it's
only the very
great the really great Masters who
really grasp emptiness that they become
seed freaks you know they're like all
concerned about you know what kind of
seed is it going to make make if I if I
blow my nose too loud and it bothers the
person next to me what kind of seed does
that make if you Michael what kind of
chic result does that have you know no
they become obsessed
by by not disturbing others in the
slightest way like a person who
understands seeds gets up in the cabin
and tiptoes to the bathroom and turns
the knob slowly you know no I'm not
kidding I'm really not kidding and they
open it as silent as a cat and then they
go in if you're a boy you sit down to
pee I'm not kidding I'm not kidding cuz
it might disturb someone and you don't
want that seed you just don't want that
seed you know and so a person who really
understands emptiness becomes B you
about Karma they become like a newly wed
bride they're afraid to do anything
wrong you know they're like
totally sensitive to how their actions
are going to what do you call it in
impinge on others totally totally
sensitive all the time so basically
they're moving to the world in this
Grace graceful dance this graceful
kind uh considerate dance I think the
big word that would
describe uh a person who understood
emptiness well would be considerate
they would be highly considerate of
others all the time
okay and that's a barometer of your
emptiness understanding
okay anybody understands
emptiness they are okay they are
considerate to
others
okay and then n AR said the same thing
in his scripture the root text on wisdom
mul PR he
said if it's the case that there's
nothing in the world which is not coming
from your seeds
then if it's the case that there's
nothing in the world that's not coming
from your seeds then it's also the case
that there's nothing in the world which
is not
emptiness that's an overstatement okay
that's an exaggeration but he's trying
to make a point okay I'll say it again
if it's the case that there's nothing in
the world that's not coming from
seeds then it's the case that there's
nothing in the world that is not
emptiness
itself so what they're trying to do is
get you to draw a close connection
between emptiness and karmic Seas like
you got to start thinking of them as
flip sides of the same coin and and you
just can't think of one without the
other okay seeds don't mean nothing if
there's no place for them to
project uh emptiness don't mean nothing
if there's no seeds to project onto it
okay also said Master CH also said in
his
all things that do anything are coming
from certain causes such
as your behavior towards others the
seeds created by your behavior towards
others the dream images that you
believed in the past are are
indefensible the Nick that is irritable
not because you've been irritable is
indefensible there you know you can't
there's no way to defend that idea
okay therefore the simple
reasoning which says that all things are
coming from your karmic seeds it cuts
all all the tra means uh Nets like the
kind of Nets you use to catch birds or
something you know this
uh what you call
twine in China there are special Nets
and then you throw them up in the air
and you catch birds I went to a forest
in in a place called uman it's 20 M walk
down the cliffs it takes 2 days and your
knees don't work again
forever uh and uh I didn't see a single
life form I didn't see a bird I didn't
see a lizard I didn't see a squirrel it
was a normal Forest it was a jungle and
I didn't see a single moving thing cuz
they use these nets and they eat
everything and they catch everything
flying crawling anything
swimming after thousands of years
there's no I don't know who eats the
leaves and stuff I don't know I didn't
see anything I didn't see a living thing
uh so TAA means a Jala sometimes in
Sanskrit uh a net okay uh so if you
understand how emptiness appears as
projections you can cut the Nets which
in which in trap you okay
M two more
minutes
CH okay we got to the quotation by jus c
i could answer questions or I could do
that I'd rather if someone had a heart
attack T night tonight that you heard
this okay very very very very beautiful
maybe the most beautiful words in all of
scripture I think and it took me a
lifetime to understand them okay it's
very very beautiful
very very famous I think
it's the three principal path so here we
go this is how Jet Cara IED all these
points and I think it's the greatest
summary ever written okay here we
go at some point in your spiritual
career the idea that nothing has any
nature of its own and the idea that
whatever you see and things is coming
from your mind will stop
alternating okay like we have trouble
holding our minds on both ideas at the
same time either I understand that
Nick's not coming from
himself or I understand that he's coming
from the seeds in my mind but those
understandings alternate in a normal
person you can think for a while how
there's a Nick that wasn't really there
which is emptiness right and then you
can think how the Nick you do see is
coming from you but somehow you can't
hold both those ideas at the same time
they kind of have to toggle then he
says at some point the toggling will
stop at some point the toggling will
stop just by understanding how Nick is
coming from the seeds in your
mind the way you used to look at him in
the past will be
destroyed okay the way you used to see
him in the past what's the way he used
to see him in the past when Nick was
irritable it was because of him and not
because of me okay and that's the cause
of all your suffering you blame it on
the other person
right once you
understand what start of right
me without fail without
exception uh that is always coming from
you okay
always that will destroy the way used to
look
at
they when you reach that
point the development of your worldview
is
complete the development of your
worldview is complete
okay he's not what he what I thought he
was that's the white
screen but rather he's coming from how I
treat other people that's the projection
of a Nick okay and when they become one
thing
and you no longer toggle between those
two
understandings your world view is
perfect you can
rest you got you got it right that's a
pretty big deal right
uh now here's the clinching
moreover understanding how he really
came to be
will eliminate your tendency to think he
exists I told you you had to figure that
out that's not my problem it should have
been the
opposite should have been the opposite
okay understanding how he's my
projection should have prevented me from
thinking he doesn't exist but that's not
how it goes understanding that he is my
projection prevents me from thinking he
does exist you have to chew on that
okay you have to cook it
and the
understanding that he's not who I
thought he was will prevent you from
thinking he doesn't
exist and it should have been the
opposite in you know it's very it's a
core you have to think about it struggle
with it
okay the understanding that he's empty
of being who I thought he was will
prevent me from thinking he's nobody
okay it's
difficult if you finally
grasp how emptiness expresses itself as
things causing other things
whoa okay if you understand how
emptiness expresses itself as certain
things causing other things specifically
your seeds causing things right
if you understand how emptiness
expresses itself that
way you will
never your view will never be stolen
away your correct view will never be
lost you will never have your correct
view
perined that's not so
good
uh your your correct view of the world
will never be stolen away okay you'll
never be robbed of your correct
view and you will turn in means you will
never fall into those two extremes okay
so you got to go over that you got to
chew on that okay you got to think about
that if you want to look it up in the
English it would be page
B right there is where the quote breaks
okay
I'm not sure how the person I'm jealous
of had translated it but I'm sure it's
okay
[Laughter]
okay this is where it gets into the
point we were talking
about a person who understands that
emptiness and the way their world is
projected by their seeds are actually
not only not contradictory but they are
necessary sides of the same coin they
they complement each other the fact that
things are not what you
thought and the fact that they are
coming from your seats are not only not
contradictory they compliment each other
okay Dr
uh at some point you'll see that there's
a a union of those two and they become
one
thing like the blank screen and the
movie projected onto it which is not
difficult to imagine right as one single
unit the projected image and the white
screen creating a movie
okay one
thing if you can get to that
point then you will gain a faith in the
process of cause and effect meaning the
fact that things are coming from the
seeds in your mind okay the process of
cause and effect I don't care that seeds
make
watermelons that's not what cause and
effect's talking about it's a form of
cause and effect it's not the one we're
talking about we're talking about you're
mean to somebody and then people seem
mean to you okay all right very
simple okay that's the one I wanted to
get to before 9:30 and I did
it
uh see joke
means I want to say it right let me
think your life
will you will lay a greater importance
than ever on ethical
Behavior you will lay a greater
importance than ever on ethical Behavior
if you understand emptiness the more you
understand emptiness the more ethical
you have to be because you're making
because that's the
projector
okay ethical I mean morality okay it's
just don't bug other people don't
impinge on other people you know be
considerate put yourself in their place
and don't do anything you wouldn't want
them to do to
you
okay generally speaking you'll become
more interested in not doing things that
hurt other people and you'll get more
interested in doing things which help
them
and you will get more
interested in following the teachings
and perfecting the teachings on how to
develop compassion how to develop love
how to develop
Boda and the and the related
vows okay the vows the body vows you'll
get much more interested in this if you
what understand emptiness the more you
understand emptiness the more interest
you'll take taking your body of us
okay means
what T can mean skillful means okay you
could misread this as skillful
means you could you could read it as
meaning to know the way to know the
method K you could read it as skillful
means that would be wrong okay here t
means okay what's T the
first three and a half Perfections what
sh the second two and a half Perfections
there are six
Perfections the first three or the first
four I like to say the first three and a
half are relate to
what you do the last two and a half
relate to how you understand what you
do for
example if you
give this a very typical in a DCI
presentation we'll be overseas we'll get
up in front of a big crowd of
businessmen Sun Island okay we at Sun
Island you were there yeah so it's just
like corporate Resort and they do
corporate Retreats and and they had the
whole corporate stuff there they were
tough they start out like this you
know uh I think the corporate staff was
required to go which is always bad and
uh so here's this cuckoo American guy
talking about you
know uh that if you give away your money
you'll make more money America you know
and then uh
and then naturally when you take off on
that tangent you will get more money if
you help others with your money more
then of course the objection arises in
any normal person's mind well I've seen
lots of people give away money and
they're all broke they're broke as a
result of doing away money you know uh
or I've seen people be generous and
people just took advantage of them you
know so what about that they should be
rich you know so then that's tough
without sh they they did the right thing
but they didn't understand what they
were doing okay and that that means y
means y in the second line here
means they cannot be divorced from each
other y means divorced y means they
cannot be divorced from each other
what you can't do good deeds without one
without understanding what's going on
otherwise they don't work so good they
will work they will work extremely slow
and they'll work to a very small extent
you will get an extra 25 cents just
before you die
okay and you won't even connect it to
what you did 30 years before okay
uh the the irony of of uninformed
generosity is that the result comes so
late that you can't relate it to what
you did to get
it see you don't remember the kindness
you paid to get the result now because
it was so poorly executed that the time
Gap was huge and and then you don't draw
a connection between getting the extra
25 cents and having been generous in the
past okay so what's more ideal is that
someone
understands the mechanics of
giving and then it will come fast so so
then you know in an extreme case and
we've seen it you know in our little
personal lives that we'll like we will
like what do you call we'll sweat over a
decision to take a loss on a talk or
something or like this Retreat you know
we'll sweat over a decision to to take a
loss on the retreat you know and not
even mention it to people just we'll
take the loss you know all we'll all
empty our bank accounts we'll all load
up our credit cards and we'll just take
the loss and we won't tell anybody and
then uh
we sweat over that kind of thing cuz it
happens about every other day
uh and then and then you know at 7:00
we'll have an epiphany and we'll say
okay let's just take it happened in
Guang Joo big time we were going to lose
$50,000 or something and then we said
what the hell let's just let everybody
come to the retreat you know lose money
lose money so you know we we decide
we'll take the loss we Guang Joe we
decide we'll take the loss and we take
the L and we get on the plane and we
have to stop in high pay on the way
home we somebody says can I have a
meeting with you in the airport on the
way home and we're like come on I mean
we've been on the road a month you know
it's 4:00 a.m. for us in the morning you
know and you want us to have a meeting
in the airport with you and they said
please please you know we're like okay
so we we land in the
airport uh we meet these people like
we're we're like laying on the table
like that and they're all perky and um
and then they hand us the money that we
lost a few hours before they just hand
it to them they say you
know do you need 30,000 bucks you know
we're
like not in an extreme
example if
you're if you understand karmic seeds
well if you have up to go with pup
if you have wisdom to go with method if
you have knowledge to accompany your
good deeds then the results are very
fast then the results are very very fast
okay so he's saying here never let them
be divorced from each other okay never
practice them exert yourself and
practicing them together
okay meaning understand the emptiness of
what you're doing and it will work
faster that's all okay he's saying
people who understand emptiness are not
only more considerate and more
moral but also stuff happens faster for
them okay they do everything with the
knowledge of where things are really
coming from and then stuff works for
them okay and they have
weird the night we started ACI Phoenix
$150,000 check came in the
mail the night we started the first
program
you know we didn't have any money for
the the program in Phoenix we didn't
have any money we just did it you know
and then the check came that night some
guy passed away and left us
$150,000 anyway okay
Dam
unfortunately there are people in the
world who consider the teachings on
morality to be Dharma simplon
stuff okay if you have a bunch of
students who can't understand emptiness
or they don't they're never going to get
through the nine levels of meditation
then teach them not to hurt other people
stick to that kind of stupid stuff there
are people who you know believe that the
teachings
on on treating others with care are are
naive and what do you call them
therefore green tender feet therefore
greenhorns therefore for beginners
they're not for advanced
tantar okay
and then they they go to their students
and they say look I have a secret High
tantric instruction to give you what
M there is no need to be ethical you're
beyond that you're in the realm of the
is you know you are operating in sheer
emptiness so why why do you have to obey
all those ethical rules you're beyond
them okay they they like take the
student aside and say you're really
special and I hereby release you from
Karma and effect you know okay you're
you're above all
that you are no different from a
charvaka okay what's a
charvaka charvaka was a school in
ancient India of all the schools of
ancient India Hindu Muslim Buddhist
Christian Jew there were lots of Jews on
the south west coast the Malabar Coast
there are still toras carved on brass
that exist in those places you know St
Thomas made it to North Western India
tuilla somebody I was talking to
Caroline right Caroline we were talking
she went to tuxill recently so
anyway uh there were all those great
holy religions in India but there was a
SE called a chak okay they said there's
no need for
Morality uh there's no Karma and there's
no consequences of karma you could do
whatever you want and it's not going to
have any effect on you and they also
denied future lives they said you know
the way you act towards others has no
effect on what happens to you after die
so so they were considered the I don't
know the stupidest of all sex to ever
appear in the 5,000 years since the vas
you know they were considered the the
dumb heads of the dumb heads so then fa
is saying these big tantas who get up
and tell their students you know you are
Beyond
morality they are they are worse than
the CH yeah they are worse than them
they are Tibetan High Tibetan llamas and
they're worse than the than the dumb
heads of
History
okay okay that's a good place to stop
because next next
is we have
completed the proof that Nick is not
Nick you are finally
freed okay
okay y he did a good
J but that also applies to Laura not
Laura and Miriam is not Miriam Amy is
not okay Amy is not you have
to understand that uh we're talking
about you yourself okay we were just
picking on Nick cuz he was sitting right
there uh
so we finished proving that you are not
yourself okay and now we have to go on
to prove that stuff is not stuck okay we
we did it with you and now we got to
talk about the rest of stuff in the
world okay so we're going to go
carefully to the rest of the stuff in
the world and check whether it is what
it seems to be and then we're finished
okay people and
stuff
and then we pretty much covered
everything okay all right it is
extremely good karma and it's extremely
rare to have a group of people who would
even want to hear this or would listen
with such attention and I think uh
intention to carry it out attention and
intention so uh thank you for that and
and you're amazing we're we're it's a
rare Karma extremely rare Karma and I I
haven't taught this in my whole life
uh it's
a it it it has happened it has come
together and and you are worthy of it
and it's it's nice and I I feel really
happy extremely happy like
extremely all right here we
go Ellen you got one
the in
[Music]
so
okay good